hello welcome to Brandon sanderson's
writing Science Fiction and Fantasy
lecture Series this is lecture number
five we're going to talk about character
today how to make your characters
interesting a question that most of my
classes in college never answered I want
to answer it to you and I think that we
do that by having characters that are
proactive uh characters that are
relatable and uh characters that are
capable and we will talk about that now
hey here we are for the writing lecture
for character uh Brandon's writing
lecture series um you might notice that
we are in a different location for those
who are watching the YouTube uh version
of this after the fact well Utah has had
a snow apocalypse uh the first big snow
of the year all right someone from
Canada over here is
like not as big but first big snow of
the air I was worried as I came to work
uh this morning which for me is like 1
um p.m.
that I didn't want my students to have
to um go through it to get to school
today uh that we can do this online we
have the technology we have the power so
we are at Dragon steel HQ the students
are watching this um theoretically on
YouTube how many do we have so far 96 96
half of the students are watching this
on uh on YouTube we hope the other half
will get there if you have friends who
are uh supposed to be here text them and
say you still need to take your quiz um
so yeah um some of them might have
decided this is their skip week because
too much snow um but we decided to do
this here and make things easier on
everyone um so we are going to talk
character if you missed the news if
you're watching this after the fact we
had some technical difficulties with the
guest lecture last week so we're going
to have to let my special extra Q&A fill
in for that um but we will figure those
out uh hopefully that won't happen again
um and we'll figure out what we're going
to do if I'm going to lecture twice on
character or what but today we're just
going to jump in to my first character
lecture as if we hadn't had a substitute
uh and so we are going to talk about
what makes a compelling character and
those of you who are uh watching not
after the fact but live right now which
is the students uh please um save up
some questions I'll ask you for some
questions Rachel Lynn is here ready to
read your comments and I will get to
your questions and things like that we
have a small peanut gallery of uh of
employees who sometimes listen to me uh
wax poetic about these things and so you
might still hear some people in here and
they might throw questions at me as well
so let's start with a story
all right um I decided that I wanted to
be really professional and give this a
go uh as I believe I told you all like
right after I got back from my mission
in uh Korea I'm like I'm a
sophomore I used to be a chemistry
major I that's not for me I'm going to
jump Whole Hog into becoming a novelist
and I'm going to start writing and I'm
going to change my major to English and
I'm going to take every writing class
they'll let me because I need to learn
how to do this I need to be a writer um
so changing my major to English not
necessarily something you have to do uh
in fact some authors recommend that you
don't do it because having a great and
interesting uh thing that you're
studying that you're excited about
giving you information and background
for telling stories can be really really
a big advantage in fact as my first
tangent of the night I would recommend
whatever you're passionate about start
thinking about how that could inform a
character or an arc or a worldbuilding
element or something like that uh a lot
of the very best books come out of
places of passion that you may not think
relate to what you're doing okay some
point Dan Wells and I are driving home
from writing group one uh day many years
ago and he started going off on serial
killers and how cool they are because
Dan's a weirdo and I know some of you
are as well and just like how
interesting it is that there's like this
three things that most serial killers
all share it's like there I'm not going
to mention them here because they're
some of them are horrific but there's
like three attributes that as children
they all shared and he was just going
off and I'm like Dan you're so
interested in this why haven't you
written about this ever at the time he
was writing Epic Fantasy uh unpublished
and he's like I really should and he sat
down and he wrote the first John cleever
novel which is the first novel that he
sold and his strongest novel that had he
had written in all those years um and
you see this happening time and time
again whatever people are passionate
about whatever hobby they have whatever
their life experience is can translate
when people say write what you know it's
an old adage they aren't necessarily
meaning that strictly you know write
your own life experience
uh if you could only write what you know
then none of us could write about
dragons right though the idea of taking
what you are passionate about and
constructing narrative around it that is
really really handy and if we're going
to be talking about character giving
like as you become more and more of a
writer you will notice that there's some
Quirk that you have or that a family
member of yours has or an odd passion
they have that you'll have a light bulb
where you're like why have I never used
that I thought I'd plumbed everything
I'm going to use that next time and then
build a character around it so um
regardless I went to college thinking
all right they're going to teach me how
to write and I started taking creative
writing classes Rachel Lynn how often in
creative writing classes do they talk
about how to create a compelling
character never never that is correct I
went to these classes and
university courses on writing what like
the number one thing that I would think
that I would want to learn from them is
how do you write a character that's
compelling no professors ever talked
about that until I took Dave's class
they never touched on it and it's still
to this day baffling to me that like one
of the core ideas of what makes people
want to read is not even touched on in
the majority of courses that you would
take at the University they can do some
really good things for you they will
talk a lot about different styles of
pros and you will end up trying a lot of
different styes of pros and settling in
to the ones that you like they will talk
about how to adapt your life experience
they're pretty good at that they will
give you opportunities for networking
and feedback on your work in fact most
of uh upper level so after your 200s
like your 300 level and up courses are
all all going to be workshops that are
going to focus on feedback and
workshopping and you know that can be
very handy uh teach you to to take the
feedback but I thought I would get
lectures on how to create a compelling
character and I never got one until my
last year when I took Dave's class and
thank goodness I did um because you know
he talked about those things so that's
what we're going to talk about today how
do you what makes a character compelling
how do you write a compelling and
interesting character and over the years
I've thought about how to present this a
great uh a great deal what are what are
my methods and how do I view it oh I'm
getting oh oh how fancy we are we used
to have a pillow bounding me to tell me
to not go before that uh otherwise it'll
get out of focus now we have a piece of
tape like they do in the movies so I'm
going to keep looking down and walking
to my Mark it's a very professional when
in movies you see someone look down and
walk and then stop and then look up they
they they love that um you walk to your
Mark um okay so we're going to talk
about this and I've I've found a lot of
different ways to present this my
favorite is around these ideas of three
key core attributes that make a
character compelling um and there are
many ways to write this many ways to
talk about this but this is my framework
I believe that characters um that are
compelling and interest about are
interesting because a mixture of three
key elements they are
proactive they are
relatable and they are capable right uh
and I made them so they kind of rhyme um
so that's how you can tell that I'm a
professional is is when my when my my
little lessons uh you know all come
together they they they they have some
sort of alliteration so um we're going
to go through these and kind of talk
about them in turn the key thing to
understand is most characters do are not
do not have all three once in a while
they do and we'll talk about characters
that do most of the time compelling
characters as a rule of thumb the type
of rule of thumb that has never followed
one to one but you can kind of think of
it as in one of these they're very high
in one of these they're moderately low
and in one of these they are growing and
learning and just your easy rule of
thumb is picking where they need to
learn where they are already strong and
where they're going to remain uh where
where they uh are not very good and it's
going to remain one of the things that
just characterizes them over time
um so proactivity we'll talk about
proactivity for minute and then we'll go
to questions from you
guys this is probably the single thing
that makes a character readable in a
story when we go into
Stories We want to see progress I talked
about that right that's not the only
thing we want to see we want to see a
lot different stuff and there are great
stories that make very slow progress and
still work really really well Jonathan
strange and Mr Nell is not about
progress in the same way that um the
born identity is about progress all
right keep in mind that different
stories try to do different things but
in general I'm going to grab my notes
Here one of the main things in fact the
number one thing you can
do to make a character interesting to
read about is to make them proactive in
such a way that they move the plot
forward so that you are able to you will
naturally bond to them because they're
making the story happen you like the
story you want the story to happen you
get frustrated by the characters who are
obstacles to the story happening you get
annoyed when someone slows and stalls
what you think should be the progress of
the story and you get excited by people
who Advance it so classic hero Pro
proactive hero is somebody who an
external conflict happens to and they
are the person who jumps up and starts
solving the problems um and we bond to
that proactivity and it's a kind of a
little bit of a hack for starting a
story if you instantly want someone to
to be uh relatable or to well
relatability one you just want someone
who's readable right at the beginning
the person who starts taking action lost
is an excellent example of this uh the
TV show Lost um which is quite good has
a some hiccups in the second season but
actually later seasons are pretty good
they get a they get a bad RP um
fantastic first season just knocks it
out of the park and a really excellent
first half of a second season then there
was a rider strike and some things
happened second season to third season
but they recovered and did really good
job so in Lost there's a character named
Jack he is a doctor they wrote the
initial pilot for it to have him die at
the end of the pilot they were actually
they had actually uh were casting Bert
Reynolds a big star to be their Jack
right and they got their screenplays
done they started workshopping them and
they realized
what happens in the beginning of loss
there's a plane crash people are getting
pulled out of the ocean everything's
chaos one person stands up and takes
charge he is the Healer he gets people
healed he gets people away from the
damage he makes a camp he is in charge
and they realize nobody cares about
anybody else but Jack because he is
proactive he's not super relatable if
you watch like the whole the entirety of
Lost Jack is one of the least relatable
characters in the entire show right he
might be the least relatable lead but
he's proactive and we'll get to
capability H he knows what to do one of
Jack's flaws is he doesn't know as well
as he thinks he does he's actually in
the middle of this one he's working on
this one and he's really good at this
one he will solve a problem even if he
solves it the wrong way we bond to that
and they all got together and you can
listen them talk about this uh in in
commentaries and they're like we can't
kill Jack we can't cast Bert Reynolds or
whoever it was I think it was Bert
Reynolds might have been someone else we
can't oh no it was Tom celic I think
anyway they're in cast somebody big uh
big ER for the time this is the early
2000s I don't know who it was somebody
big they're like we can't cast someone
that we have to pay every episode to be
in every episode we need
this is our this is our Center um
because he is so proactive Michael
Keaton it was Michael Keaton okay it was
Michael Keaton so even even better right
yeah paying for Michael Keaton at that
point uh big deal right and
so they recast and I don't even know if
they gone to Michael Keaton right this
was all in kind of the early
brainstorming stages but you sometimes
write a role to somebody they had
planned a big star who would then so
they could have you know this big star
open their story and they they rebuilt
the whole thing it's all because of this
one there there is also the problem with
proactivity what we call the villain
problem in a lot of Stories the villain
is
proactive and the hero is reactive or
the protagonist this is especially true
of like origin stories where a villain
is out doing something awesome and
a potential hero is fussing around like
you know being afraid of bats um and
having you know daddy issues and
meanwhile you got this this person who
is absolutely reprehensible right you
know no moral code whatsoever um though
I would argue a lot of them they have a
few Hallmarks of relatability they're
just you know the moral code one which
goes under this notot uh they don't even
have to be that good at what they're
doing sometimes they are Joker obviously
was very good the opening scene to dark
Knight's job is to show you how capable
he is but also how proactive he is and
you end up with these stories where the
villains are more interesting because
the villains are doing stuff they move
the story they get stuff done and
because of that people bond to the
villains because they're proactive
they're you know they're trying they're
out there doing their best to destroy
the world
and you know the the the hero is like oh
I don't know the Call to Adventure ah
but my pillow is so soft you know like
so we Bond so that's what we call the
villain problem so how do you overcome
this um well you might be saying
Brandon uh proactivity seems the one
that most characters are going to work
on right because we talked about the
hero's journey and other things a lot of
times at the beginning of the story a
character has to be forced to be
proactive right Luke Skywalker wants to
go up in the clouds and in the stars but
really his his family has problem even
really getting him to go go get the
droids right he is a dumb teenager who
doesn't want to do anything he wants to
dream about having done stuff um you
know this is a lot of characters so how
or it's the villain problem my
protagonist is a good person which means
they want to hang out with their family
and you know read books uh while they're
cat purs that's what they want to do
with their life and so the villain has
to be the proactive one well there's a
few counters to this if you don't want
proactivity to be the thing the
character's working on which sometimes
you do but a lot of times you don't
usually you want the character working
in your classic sense they're working on
something down here uh they're getting
better at this or they're working on
some sort of uh personal flaw that they
have sometimes you want them to work on
being proactive um sometimes that's your
act one thing that by the end they have
learned to be proactive a lot of times
it's like your midpoint your character
moves from inactive to proactive but you
can do a lot of things to move them up I
imagine these as like three sliding
skills um we'll put these around sill
here thank you Steve Argy who came and
played magic with us and Drew a picture
of s so if you got your p and your R and
that's okay C I was going to say if
that's a k then we just spelled out um
uh North Korea uh right PR PRK People's
Republic in North Korea and that what it
is PRC doesn't spell anything that's
going to embarrass me on the internet
does it um China oh it's China I was
thinking China it is PRC it is PRC
PC there
that does now now watch that spell
something even more embarrassing um CPR
CPR right yeah we like
CPR all right yeah there we are yeah
yeah no one can can CH choose me yeah
see p r CP CPR CPR we like CPR um all
right so I imagine these are sliding
scales um where a character kind of is
at the beginning of the story at one
point on all three of these and is at a
different point and at least one of them
at the end the the real truth is and
we'll get to this later is there's like
particularly for um for relatability and
uh for capability you usually have
multiple in fact even Pro for
proactivity right my wife if a if a
lesson needs to be taught she was a
teacher if somebody needs to be trained
she will step up be proactive and create
the lesson plan and get it done but if
if you got in a room and said someone
needs to beat Super Mario to save the
world she does not
volunteer I guess that's a capability
but you know there are certain areas
where we're proactive right um she'll be
very proactive in organizing things for
her family group uh or for her business
but in other uh areas she will not be
proactive so we we all are like that but
here's some tips to move someone up on
the proactive
scale a little bit um Kurt vonet says
that one of the keys to making an
interesting story is to make a Cara your
character want something at the start
even if it's just a cup of
coffee whatever it is make them want
something um I'm convinced no one's seen
this movie it's better than its
reputation but it's not amazing it's
like one of these movies that's in
between bad and good so in places it's
so bad it's good in other places it's
just good good and that's Hudson Hawk
never even do you like it it's awesome
okay it is awesome movies that are that
are so bad they're good in some places
and then legitimately good in other
places are just awesome equilibrium is
the same way right um yeah come on when
the face gets cut off that's so bad it's
good that is not just legit good that's
so bad it's good yeah right um so uh
Hudson Hawk is the same way few n of
people in that I'm convinced they heard
this cuz uh Bruce Willis wants a cup cup
of coffee and every time he picks one up
he gets shot or something disastrous
happens all he wants is a cup of coffee
that whole movie just let poor Bruce
Willis get a cup of coffee and he
doesn't get his cup of coffee until the
end yeah spoilers um but I've I've
always been convinced that they heard
this Kurt Von quote and they're like oh
that's a good idea that's what he wants
is a cup of coffee admit to me in Hudson
Hawk the woman doing an imitation of a
dolphin is so bad it's good yes Annie
McDow imitating a
dolphin I mean it's not easy to make
those noises it's not easy to make those
noises but anyway um awesome movie I
don't know if it's a good movie but it
is awesome it's it's in that special
category um make people want something
normally it's not a cup of coffee
normally this is going to relate in some
way to what makes them relatable or uh
to their their capability in some way
but normally it's just like what are
their
motivations we don't talk enough about
character motivations I think uh in
discussions of narrative because the
difference between a wooden character
and a well-rounded fleshed out character
in The Reader mind
is almost always motivation issues it's
not actually that their dialogue is as
stilted as you think it is it's not
always that you know when a character is
off to a reader not to a professional
they'll look at these different ways but
when a person reads a character like
just didn't work for me it's I would say
six times out of 10 it's a motivation
problem meaning you have not accurately
indicated what the character wants uh
and shown us how their actions are born
out of the things they want in fact most
characters should want multiple things
some of them self-contradictory because
we're human beings and that's how we are
um and as they want those things their
desires uh should inform their actions
which we should be able to figure out so
that as they change and their desires
change and their actions change it makes
sense to us um a lot of times if you're
like this character just doesn't feel
alive well you've established one
motivation and then they're doing
something else sorry to harp on The Last
Jedi but Finn really wants to go help
his friend
Ray this movie wants him to go save
horses from a casino um and the movie
does not establish enough that we want
him to swap to saving horses instead of
like they had you know and part of this
is the problem with movie one they had
good chemistry either is not necessarily
even as romantic but as friends great
chemistry we like seeing those two
characters on screen together we make a
promise at the beginning he's going to
be back and we're going to have some of
those more fun times and the motivations
just never work for him to the point
that at the end of the movie he tries to
you know Ram his ship into uh something
that we're just like I no longer
understand Finn but I guess okay heroic
sacrifice oh no you weren't anyway we
won't get into the last shedi oh that
movie oh that movie um
anyway um making your characters
proactive um making them want something
explaining their motivations um and
remember that in narrative particularly
at the beginning when you're making your
promises small things of evoke the
larger
things right a character does not want
to have to want to save the world at the
beginning but if they love their
family and you really establish that
then you will establish that um when
they make the decision to go out and
save the world that it makes sense
showing that Mulan has a special
relationship with her father who is is
wise and seems to get her when no one
else does leads exactly to her going out
on a big adventure she doesn't want a
big adventure but she doesn't want her
dad to have to go to war so you can see
little thing establishing the
relationship between mother and father
leads to now I'm going to save the
kingdom because you know I'm Mulan and
I'm good at saving kingdoms apparently
um right Little Things evoke the larger
if your character is going to be not
very proactive they're going to resist
the call in some ways that's fine but if
you can show them proactive in their own
life in certain ways mulan's another
good example she has to feed the
chickens what does she do she comes up
with a cool plan and she feeds the
chickens in a cool way we're like you
are solving problems Mulan We want to
watch you solve more problems and lo and
behold through the whole film she is
solving problems with her wits in
interesting ways that make us excited to
watch do things like that with your
character even if they aren't in a
position to save the world at the
beginning they don't have to be the jack
that at the beginning there's a giant
plane crash takes charge and saves
everyone if that's not your character
that's fine but if you zoom in on one
character helping another person get to
Shore and you know making that decision
predictively you can show them turning
around seeing someone else in danger
going back and getting them that's
proactivity for the beginning of the
story to give you a seed and to make you
start to build this
one okay let's do questions on
proactivity before we get to
relatability and uh capacity so uh do we
got anything over here or do we got
anything from panut Gallery um I have a
couple from the chat couple from the
chat and I will try to speak loud so
people can hear I will repeat the
question okay how do you create
proactivity in a situation that limits
the character's ability to take action
yeah how do you create productivity in a
situation where character's um limited
to take action let's take a classic
example person is in prison they are
very very limited anyone read count of
money
Christo is he proactive being in prison
no not in he cannot be proactive um so
you either start showing some of these
other things or you ease into it um over
time he meets someone he makes a plan he
realizes that he can get out right
someone who is limited you can at least
show they're like I'm going to try
something a lot of these um things will
start with a character like I am locked
up I can't do anything I'm going to at
least try something they try some uh
situation where they're like I'm going
to get out of my situation by playing
sick well the guards are on to that
that's too they're too smart for that
but you tried right your character
um they are if if it's external keeping
them from being proactive you can do all
kinds of things they can think about
what are they going to do what are they
going to do they get out um what are
their plans they can even go so you can
be like I want I'm in this terrible
situation can I talk to the guards and
to give me extra bread right you can do
all kinds of things from a person in a
uh situation what's more difficult is
when the internal limitations are forced
making it hard for them to be proactive
I've often said that the most difficult
character to write and that might be a
hard Pro there's a whole bunch of I
things that can be difficult to write
but uh I've often said the most
difficult or at least one of the most
difficult is somebody whose mental
health um makes it very difficult for
them to be proactive or care about
anything these are difficult stories to
write they just are um I've talked
before about um mistborn 3 uh spoilers
uh for mbor 3 minor spoilers uh but I've
talked before about I think even in this
class about seed um at some events at
the end of Miss born 2 drive one of the
prot main character protagonists into a
deep
depression um and I wrote the entire
book with him just in this deep
depression and it was written really
authentically I did all my research and
people had so much trouble getting
through those chapters now that be what
you want right these are all things if
you want to make a comp character a
certain way here's how you do it doesn't
mean that that's the only way to write a
character but looking at it I realized
oh man people I need people to like
these scenes for reasons that are very
important to the ending of mbor 3 and so
I went back and I rewrote them all so
that he was sliding into
depression sliding into depression and
what he was doing was he'd had a crisis
of faith he was searching for the true
uh True Religion and in the initial
draft there wasn't that search happening
uh he'd already determined that there
you know that he he' lived a lie and
nothing you know there was no truth out
there and the story I rewrote it so he's
like I'm going Point by point for all
these religions that I've memorized and
I'm determining if this might possibly
be the right one which gives progress he
is this much way through and he's
sinking further in depression and the
like you feel him getting worse and
worse motion is good even if it's
downward motion static is what is hard
to write and the scenes work way better
they're still sometimes hard to get
through but there's motion and it's
downward motion and it's Soul crushing
but the motion works and it was one of
the big important revisions so if you
want to do this there's a there's a
couple things you may just want to admit
proactivity is not a thing they can do
then you focus on these two right if you
still want to be proactive find a way
that they are forced by something to be
proactive or something they can control
someone who's bedridden um because of a
of a physical health problem can still
be very proactive in saying you know I'm
going to keep my family together by
being positive when they're around or
things like this and maybe that's bad
maybe it's good but they can make that
plan and execute it you can have people
be proactive in their small sphere of
influence the big dangerous one is that
uh mental health you know as realistic
as it is it is just a challenge to write
uh in a book and make it uh make it work
so other
question well you answered a few that um
let's see yes I'm I am curious um when
looking at proactivity and a character
is say act one blocked by the hard
challenge how do you restart proactivity
within a char
okay they've they've lost their
proactivity because they hit a hard
challenge uh character is therefore kind
of forced into inactivity uh because
they're second guessing themselves and
how do you restart that uh boy you know
Donald I think that there are like a
dozen ways you could do this and it
would be individual to the story um what
I see a lot of times happening in those
situations is we usually cut to someone
else being the proactive one for a
little while even if they're in the same
group and then someone has to pull them
out of it or they have to pull out of it
and this works really well when you have
a large cast and you can have one person
go this happened in oathbringer right we
have one per person go through something
just enormously traumatic and someone
else we jump to their Viewpoint and we
pull them along through it while they're
dealing with it um but there's all sorts
of things that can do this like a lot of
times you'll see this at the end of act
two beginning of act three the
characters gone G through their darkest
moment and they just they've given up um
this is a really great time to have the
last bit of character growth they need
in some way where something they've
learned along the way comes back to them
and they they decide to make one final
push and that happens really well ALS
that happens really yeah that works
really well as well anything else over
here um what about characters who
deliberately do the opposite like see
someone drowning and let them drown is
that still proactive yes so what if they
do the opposite they see someone
drowning and they let them drown that
counts is proactive unless they are
frozen in fear right they can't act
they're not letting saving them because
of a flaw related to their own
proactivity but if it's like ah we'll
let them drown I'll be able to get you
know I need to take care of myself well
that's going to pull them down on
relatability it's not really going to
influence their proactivity in my
experience so yeah is it confusing to
write two characters that have competing
proactivity where they're competing to
is it confusing to write two characters
have competing Pro activities no that's
awesome it works really well in fact
um this is why the fugitive Works The
Fugitive is an excellent example of what
we call I just talked about it in the
Q&A for for last week uh what we call a
cat and mouse um uh
mystery uh often times mystery fall into
a lot of different formats cat and mouse
is where two people are striving for
either opposing or similar goals and one
is trying to catch the other one before
you know before the first one can
achieve their goals and so you'll watch
the fusive is an ex excellent example of
character a Harrison Ford is trying to
catch the one-armed man while character
B Tommy Lee Jones is trying to catch
character a both are proactive both are
brilliant they both make really smart
moves and you get to watch them
having opposing one needs to stay free
to to find the killer the other needs to
catch him because he thinks he is the
killer uh and they both get to be super
proactive uh they both get to be super
capable though the scary thing is Tommy
de Jones is more
capable but we know that Harrison Ford
is right and so the dramatic tension
becomes Tommy Lee Jones is so good at
this can Harrison Ford stay ahead of him
long enough to solve the problem because
Tommy Lee Jones will catch him
eventually because he is more capable
and that's the that's the fun of that
story but puts a time bomb on it but a
kind of a loose time bomb that uh that
works so we good here we're going to
move on yeah okay let me check the time
I can go all the way over to this chair
I don't know if you guys can see the
chair but that's my boundary wow that
was 40
minutes I don't have a clock in here
that I can watch all right we we'll keep
moving along
relatability uh this is the most most
obvious one when people talk about how
do you write a compelling character or
things like that they're often talking
about how do you make a character
likable uh this is pretty important
right depending on the story you're
telling you want your character
generally to have some aspect of
relatability it helps us put them it
helps us get into their shoes and um you
know go on this particularly if it's a
sci-fi fantasy story this Fantastical
Adventure or this thriller where they're
being chased you want to like the
character because if you don't like them
then the stakes tend to go down for them
because their death is not something
that's going to bother you uh so in a
life and death situation it's important
to have somebody be relatable um how do
we make someone relatable well there's a
couple of things that we do um the
number one the reason that the book save
the cat is called save the cat is
because uh showing someone show kindness
and use their proactivity or uh or
capacity in the betterment OR for good
morals to help others is instantly it
makes them relatable we generally I'm
assuming most people watching this want
to help others and be nice right we want
to make people's lives better seeing
somebody who does that and makes use of
um of you know maybe they aren't the
most capable maybe they aren't the most
proactive but they can help somebody
instantly makes us like them and the the
the term save the cat means you know if
you want to show who the protagonist is
you have them save a cat if you want to
show who the villain is you have them
kick a dog right it's just the the very
simple old adage uh which now you'll
laugh every time you see a movie where
someone saves a cat literally or where
they kick a dog literally right like I
still what's that John Wick yeah John
Wick John Wick kind of the inverse of
that I remember yeah in uh my example is
Tad Williams old school but there's like
this book series uh memory sorrow and
Thorn that I loved uh reading when I
when I was younger still very good Tad
Williams a great author um and in memory
sorrow and Thorn like at one point the
the young kid who's like a um it's a an
' 80s fantasy novel so he's like he's
like a peasant of some sort he's like
the guy who takes care of like the
fireplace and where at he's like you
know little kid in a castle whose job is
to be the servant uh he finds there's
like puppies and he finds one that's
disabled and he's like oh I'm going to
take care of this puppy and then one of
the princes walks by and goes Crunch and
steps on it cuz he's like well that one
should be killed it's not you know uh
it's not as strong as the others and
you're like oh I know who the bad guy is
and lo and behold that's the bad guy um
and oh hey thank you I got got a little
clock set up here for me um so save the
cat uh kick the dog sometimes literally
um one of the things that's under um
underappreciated I think by writers
because they all know about save The Cat
you've probably all heard about that one
of the things that will make someone
relatable is if you can see them Through
The Eyes of someone else who highlights
their good um attributes seeing this
through your own eyes is sometimes will
make the character sound a little
arrogant it could be off-putting seeing
it through someone else's eyes can be
really handy for helping us just really
see how uh how how interesting relatable
the character is
um we like what we like people that
other people like it's just a natural
instinct in us um it's pretty if you
know you don't go over the top on it
this is why um deliberately I did not
show and I think I talked about this in
class I didn't show chapter one of way
of Kings from kaladin's
Viewpoint um I wanted you to see kaladin
from the ey eyes of someone who was not
kaledin himself uh partially because
Kalin tends to be hard on himself um and
beyond that seeing this kind of just
large in the Life heroic figure through
the the eyes of someone else and then
time Jump uh spoiler like chapter 2 he's
months have past and c is now a slave
and he's lost all of that um I felt like
that was the way to show off you know
how good a person kaladin is um and to
to kind of to kind of make that work um
so liked by others but there's other
things here self-awareness is a big one
for us uh the character who is not
proactive but understands that their
lack of proactivity is a problem and is
working on it and acknowledging it we
give them a pass we're like oh you know
you poor you poor person as long as
again you're not over the top with this
you got to be careful in these things
but as long as you're not over the top
of it you're like you know what they're
working on it they're working on things
the person who's a
jerk but knows it and is working on it
and tries to be better like we fall in
love with Mr Darcy in part because he
kind of knows it and he
tries mediocrely to do better right um
and then he shows he uses his
proactivity and his Capa capability in
this case enormous wealth uh in order in
service of the protagonist at the point
in the story where you're supposed to
turn turn on dorsy Darcy mean turn
toward him uh because you realize Darcy
you know he's he's a
Kagan even though he's not old enough to
be one yet but he's trying um that can
go a great distance and
relatability uh for us um obviously
indicating some just normal basic things
that most people do or like right um why
does Garfield hate Mondays he's a cat
every day is the same to Garfield why
does he hate Mondays because his
audience theoretically hates Mondays
because they have to leave the weekend
and go to work so Garfield hates Mondays
to make him relatable because it's a
normal thing that people uh have he
likes lasagna because we all want to eat
good food in large portions and it's not
good for us like K's a cat he shouldn't
like lasagna but Garfield represents
like there's just a few key things that
make Garfield Garfield and they're
designed to make him relatable um
working with these sorts of things can
be relatable you do have to be aware
that some of these things will make them
unrelatable to a certain percentage of
the audience for instance if you have a
kid who struggles with math that is
relatable to most most people in my
experience some people are like no I
don't struggle but if you can make the
general sort of you know I I struggle to
get my projects done on time and math is
the hardest for me well that's relatable
right we all sometimes wait a little too
long to get the things done that we need
to do um and then the last one would be
morality um a moral compass that aligns
with the general moral compass of those
reading the book is going to make
someone relatable um particularly if
they're again self-aware about some of
their own flaws or how they might take
it too far or things like that just you
know it's like swimming back to get the
person right swimming back to get the
person makes someone relatable because
it shows a basic moral
decency um in general if we're talking
about our sliding scales I lost oh it's
in my back pocket you will end up having
you know your villains be very high in
proactivity and very low in relate uh
Rel relatability and often pretty high
in cap uh capability like that's your
classic villain your your classic sort
of um uh superhero villain right um but
you can have a lot of villains like if
you move them up just a little bit in
relatability those end up tending to be
the strongest villains right this is
Magneto is it relatable that Magneto
wants to kill all the
humans say
no
um is it relatable that he is afraid
that if he doesn't because of his
history being uh taken and thrown into a
concentration camp that the things that
make him different and he the people he
loves different be destroyed if he
doesn't destroy them first
kind of relatable right suddenly okay
this is this is relatable right I'm you
know this is probably why we got stupid
sexy saon in rings of power right um I I
jur I don't know if that worked but
that's probably what they were trying to
do there is you know s maybe s's better
if he's stupy stupid sexy Saron um but
you can be aware relatability and some
villain stories start someone like here
and they're on a downward
trajectory yes well yeah spoilers but
yeah um but you know there's a lot of
there's a lot of stories right like you
can you can say you know Spider-Man's uh
uh the Sam Ry Spider-Man like almost
every Spider-Man villain is this they
start here they their their tragic flaw
causes them to to take a step no one
else would take and we know is against
moral codee and then their relatability
crashes as they become uh Green Goblin
Dr Octopus uh the lizard uh Sandman all
of them this is kind of the Spider-Man
thing um right um is you know Sandman a
little bit less you you were looking at
me on Sandman sandman's pretty high on
relatability I agree he is he is he's
not he's he gets it happens to him
rather than him taking the serum or you
know uh yeah right like he he's less
crazy scientist than the rest of them uh
he's poor guy who uh is in the wrong
place but then get superpowers
regardless that's kind of what what's
going on there any questions on
relatability this is the most obvious
one I have one yes um how do you write a
good
anti-hero so uh anti-hero let's make
clear there are two definitions of
anti-hero so in the classical literary
sense an
anti-hero um Madame bovery is often held
up as an anti-hero in that she is not
ProActive at all and it's a story
happening around her and she refuses to
act and she is an anti-hero in that she
refuses to fulfill the role of
protagonist and it's supposed to make
you annoyed the entire book is about
making you annoyed that Madame bovery
won't do anything this is a classic
literary anti-hero in modern pop culture
an anti-hero is a villain who does
heroic things and those are two
different things normally like this one
go study literature if you want to have
it a classical anti-hero modern
anti-hero it's actually pretty easy you
make them highly proactive and capable
and low on relatability but then you
just have them fight people who are
lower on this one right um there's a
there's a famous adage
right driving on the road anyone who
passes you you're like they're going so
fast they're crazy anyone you have to
pass you're like how dare you impede
traffic you're so slow you're crazy
right um and this kind of applies in all
areas of life I've noticed it with
religion where however religious you are
the people who are a little more
religious you like look at those zealots
and the people a little less religious
than you are like you know they they
might need Jesus um
so yeah um so with um with anti-heroes
right you just make sure that they are
worse um like you know is John Wick a
hero he's a protagonist for sure and
dividing your mind hero and protagonist
a hero I would say is um someone who
does uh virtuous things a protagonist is
someone who's
uh we want to succeed and we're
following and hero protagonist is the
main character of snow crash
um actually that's his name um so you
guys should read snow crash it's great
um so what you do you just you make sure
that there's some even worse people out
there to turn loose on and there's a
part of us that really loves the villain
problem right we love the villains
because the is so cool to watch them you
know go crazy it's so cool to watch John
Wick right John Wick it should not be
cool to watch John Wick murder everyone
right it shouldn't but they're all bad
guys they're all bad guys and yes he was
a bad guy he was an assassin he he tried
to be good that right he starts down
here but he tries to be good he gets
inched up he gets a puppy
and then they K his do the puppy doesn't
survive um U yeah sorry but then you're
on board because you're like you didn't
just kick the dog you you made a mistake
and this is the coolest assassin ever
and it's kind of like you get to throw
away your own morals for a little while
it's okay in literature this is why we
have literature so that you get to
experience things that you would never
do yourself um and you get to watch John
Wick go crazy on these guys right and
John Wick I don't know that I would call
him an anti-hero because to really get
to anti-hero Stage you're also doing
some villainous things along the way
it's just you're doing some really bad
damage to people even more villainous so
you're kind of like it's okay um you
know that's what makes a classic
anti-hero but it depends like most of
the people that are anti-heroes in
popular fiction right Venom he just a
hero at this point Punisher he just a
hero at this point right it's an
anti-hero means you dress in
Black uh right do bad things for good
reason yeah yeah Reon yeah you maybe
still have a few pouches from the Rob
lifel days of uh of comic books uh
strapped to you in random places and you
wear black um red what's that yeah
Deadpool wears red but like the Deadpool
movies he is not an anti-hero he is a
straightup hero right like is there
anything anti-hero like Deadpool 2 no he
just as I mean okay there's a normal
person he recruits into his
team who with no superpowers and that
might be a little anti-hero um he also
saves that to get out spoiler he does
save that person so but yeah um so
anyway there you go good question
anti-hero just make them slightly more
relatable to the people that they are
going against and you'll probably be
fine if you want to be a true anti-hero
you should delve into the moral
complexities of some of the Terrible
Things they've done uh Grim dark really
leans into this um and the best Grim
dark stories are yes he's the
protagonist yes he's an anti-hero and
that I want him to succeed but he really
should deal with the fact that he did X
Y and Z and it doesn't look like he's
really going to um and that leaves you
like comp complicated feelings about
these characters uh I mean uh we talked
about it the the Q&A also Paul trades
right uh paulit trates um is a
protagonist who is um very arguably a
villain as well and you don't see it
because he's protag so much in
fulfilling the classical Heroes Journey
that by the end when he's a villain
you're like oh maybe I shouldn't have
been rooting for the entire galaxy to be
thrown into a holy war by you know but
they asked for it they killed my dad who
was the only good person around so um so
deal with it so uh any other questions
yeah um when it comes to character
tropes and relatability you is the goal
to build off of the foundation of
character tropes so that your characters
can be relatable once you have given
them the unique uh good question tropes
and I didn't get into the quirkiness
which is another one in the relatability
um so you're mostly you say tropes we
say used to say archetypes tropes are
used as archetypes now um and things
like that so um letting the reader put
someone quickly in a uh in a a pigeon
hole them and then show how they don't
quite fit that hole is a really valid
way Paul tradus is an excellent example
right he's the young nobleman you've
read this story before something
terrible happens we're going to watch
him restore right to the universe and so
the fact that he's a villain can sneak
up on you um and that is uh that is
using the tropes against the reader in
cool ways uh a lot of times you will
want to kind of the the readers will put
your character in a box automatically
and so how you decide to fight against
that is up to you you can completely
upend it by you know pulling reversals
on them or you can just be expanding
that box as they go and showing more
facets to them over time um and this is
where we get into the the quirks we do
like people who don't fit their role
it's a really natural thing same reason
we're attracted to people who are um who
are proactive and we're attracted to
people who have
capacity we are interested in people
that don't fit their role for whatever
reason because every one of us don't fit
our role for some reason that Society
has said because roles are BS and it's
just how human brains have to try to
process how the overwhelming amount of
information we have so uh that's where
your quirks come in I am like this but
this and when you can have your quirks
expand someone's role rather than just
be something wacky usually for most
stories that's better right your Quirk
is not I'll use I'll use an example from
Rachel's writing your Quirk is uh you
know her character um has this sort of
um need to prove herself right she's not
the classic Apprentice the classic
Apprentice learns her lesson in the
opening scene there's a usually you
you've seen the scene 100 times
Apprentice is trying something they get
a little big for the britches it's it's
Mickey in um uh Fantasia he tries he
fails the wizard comes back and he's
like you did wrong learn your lesson and
Mickey's like okay I'll learn my lesson
her character says nope not going to
learn that lesson I was right um You
she's in a box you expect you uh know
how her character is going to to play
out and then she breaks out of that box
a little bit and shows off her flaw um
and we're gonna we're going to get to
flaws we'll probably push that off
because we only have 15 minutes
sanderson's second law will talk a whole
bunch about flaws so we'll save it for
that lecture um but the idea of that a
character strong characters that really
work generally have expertise and flaws
in equal measure and um I've decided for
this lecture series I'm going to call
them um flaws restrictions and
limitations
so a flaw being and we'll get to this
again in serson Second Law a flaw being
uh something they need to overcome
highlighting I have this flaw this
character has this flaw their Arc is
going to be about overcoming it um a
restriction is some sort of story your
self-imposed thing that they could get
over but you don't want them to the
classic being Superman's moral code
right Superman has a restriction because
he has a moral code it makes things
harder for him
we do not want him to overcome his moral
code some stories May explore what
happens if you do uh and then
limitations by my definition are imposed
upon you against your will um and often
are physical limitations and the story
is not about fixing it but overcoming it
um if your character for instance um the
example I always use is like it's the
one-armed person who wants to play
football right the story is not about
how they should have two arms the story
is about you have this unfair limitation
well you're going to have to work with
it and uh work around it and though you
treat those three things differently so
showing that someone has a flaw actually
makes them relatable harping on it too
much and having it impede progress too
long will pull them down so that starts
a flaw as as an advantage in
relatability and over time it uh becomes
more and more liability the longer they
go without uh overcoming for instance if
Luke Skywalker after um after Obi-Wan
said you know he says You must learn the
ways of the force and looks like no I
have to go power converter and he runs
back and his family is dead and oban's
like we now need to go save the princess
he's like no I don't want it the more he
does the know I don't want to at that
point the more we're going to dislike
him early on loving his family and
feeling like he's not good enough is
relatable continuing will drive us up
the
wall um I reference lost maybe I should
talk about the Michael problem at this
point um yeah so the Michael
problem in Lost there's a character
named Michael and he was my least
favorite character he should have been
super likable because he had a really
cool flaw and a really cool like uh cap
capability
his capability was he loved his son his
flaws that he'd been a bad dad in the
past and his character Arc was I'm going
to learn to be a good dad now that
should have been a slam dunk like
compared to Jack who is like I am
Superman I will save you all do not
question um super unrelatable super
proactive you've got Michael who's just
like I just want to I want to be a bet
good dad his son gets kidnapped uh this
is season two I believe where you know
uh son gets kidnapped and his whole
character comes about getting his son
back great he's got motivation
everything should be working the problem
is when things become a character's only
attribute and it goes too far it starts
to Annoy Us and you would get to these
scenes where they'd be like all right we
need something for lunch what do you
guys want like Kate's like I want a
sandwich Sawyer's like ah you know what
give me some whiskey I'm Sawyer Michael
what do you want he's like I want my son
and they're like okay yes we understand
that what do you want for lunch my son
isn't having lunch he's kidnapped by the
others and we like okay Michael we get
it just lunch he's like my son like and
to the point that like they went too far
in writing this character's uh you know
very relatable motivation to became the
only thing to the point that everyone
was so tired of Michael nobody
lik Michael which is bizarre considering
right all right let's talk about uh
capability well we'll we'll start we'll
do that so capability another easy one
uh pretty obvious we like competent
people doing things
competently we will read entire books
about competent people doing things
competently last week I referenced dirt
pit right Dirk pit is so good at his job
of being he's just a marine biologist
guy with a with a military background
who wants to go study you know the ocean
but bad guys keep trying to destroy the
ocean and he happens to be the only one
there 27 times in a row who can stop a
terrorist organization from detonating
NES that radiate the entire ocean or
whatever right just happens he's like
James Bond if James Bond instead of
being a womanizer alcoholic was a Boy
Scout right with like degrees in puppy
petting and uh how to use assault rifles
right um and in Dirk pits I'm
exaggerating a little bit but he is just
so good at things I remember reading one
of these books I love this story like
it's one of the mid later books and I
might be exaggerating this it's been a
while but I remember reading it's from
the Viewpoint of dirt Pit's accountant
Dirk pit isn't there right dirt pit is
off stopping something it's a little
Side Story accountant is trapped without
a way off on an island with bad guys and
the accountant wants to hide in the cave
but then he thinks what would Dirk
do and so instead he kills the bad guy
steals a helicopter and escapes because
Dirk pit is so awesome by Aura of
Awesomeness his accountant becomes a
Navy SEAL right like that's how cool
Dirk pit is um we like reading about
this now most stories are not going to
lean on this nearly as much as a dir
Dirk pit or a James Bond story does and
in fact one of the things they did to
make the new James Bond more relatable
was they pulled back on how good he was
at things and showed him failing or
nearly failing a lot more often in
Casino Royale he became vulnerable again
rather than the guy that can solve all
the problems some too much uh capability
will pull down relatability but if in a
story about someone being proactive and
uh and super good at stuff we don't care
that's what the story is about right and
that's totally fine normally what you're
going to do is you're going to have
someone be really good at one or two
things and really weak at other things
and you're going to show how the things
they're good at initially help move the
plot along but the things they're bad at
become weaknesses that are exploited
their flaws their limitations um their
oh man what was the other word
their restrictions their restrictions I
never can remember that one um so what's
that a flaw it's a flaw yeah it's one of
my flaws as a teacher um and you see how
their flaws balance them out so before I
get to this question um be aware that
being good at something doesn't mean
need mean you need to be good at firing
assault rifles Sam wise gamji is largely
considered people's favorite character
and Lord of the Rings he has one
superpower other than making good food
Sam is loyal Sam is so incredibly loyal
that nothing can budge his loyalty to um
to Mr Frodo to the point that his
superpower is what Saves the World him
being loyal to Frodo and being willing
to go on this track and refusing to
leave when Frodo told him to leave leads
to him carrying froto up the mountain
and if you hadn't done that everyone's
dead right um though fun tangent the
lord of the me Lord of the Rings memes
uh subreddit is awesome my favorite one
recently is where Aragorn at the end of
the third movie is like looks back
everyone says for Frodo and starts
running and then it cuts to a steam of
all the normal guards they're like who's
froto because they don't
know and it makes you think oh yeah he
yells for froto and there's like three
guys there who even know who froto is
fortunately they're the guys that uh
that could that they really the only
other three guys they need by the way
your mama so fat when legal Los killed
her gimly counted it as two what was
your question
that was I stole that from the memes
isn't that
[Laughter]
good you're give me five oh you raised
your hand I'm like oh Taylor has a
question he hasn't had one yet no he's
got he's giv me the five minute warning
so um all right this is easy I will talk
about arcs because we only have four
minutes left an arc is where somebody is
moving up on one of these or down on one
of these uh it makes it very easy to
visualize usually
it's someone moving up on relatability
because they're working on their flaw
and that mere fact that they're working
on it like I said moves them up but when
they overcome it we chare the other most
common is you know capability somebody
is an apprentice they don't know how to
use the force but they need to use the
force luk this is a problem over time
they learn to use the force luk and they
get to blow up the That's sow Moon um
and moving up or down on one of these is
just a really great way to think about
giving a character Arc to your character
now there are other kinds of arcs right
there are working on external problems
there's relationship arcs and all these
tie into characters but purely internal
arcs usually relate to moving up or down
are one on one of these
three last questions for 3
minutes yeah we're good um we'll be in
person next week I'm still not sure if
it's going to be Q&A on uh character or
if I'm just going to do another
character lecture um we'll talk about it
next week in class until then drive
safely all of my students and I hope the
rest of you enjoyed this and start
saving up your questions for um the
online uh Q&A I just recorded the one
for plot so it should be should be up by
the time you see this so thank you
much for